Hello, everyone, and
welcome to our last lecture
in the series of lectures
on renal physiology.
And today, we will
conclude these lectures by
talking about the physiology
of urine concentration
and dilution. So, so far,
we started off talking
about the big picture,
the complete rules and
regulations that control the
bulk movement of fluids and
have narrowed the focus
down to the kidney and
then even further into the
kidney from the nephron,
going through each
individual solute and the
nephron segments that are
critical in regulating it.
And then we proceeded
to talk about what role
kidney has in acid
-base balance, which is
one of its major
functions, and the equally
major function is
regulating water output.
These are our
objectives for today. So
we'll talk about
antidiuretic hormone,
how it's regulated,
how it affects water
and solute reabsorption.
We'll talk about a
concept called the
medullary osmotic gradient
and how that contributes
to the ability of
the kidney to concentrate
and dilute urine.
So, again, we'll start off
with a scenario and similar
to a couple of scenarios,
you have exercise vigorously
on a very, very hot day
and you are feeling weird,
lightheaded, skipping beats.
You take the banana and
the coconut water, you
know, then you go to the
bathroom and you urinate
and you are just shocked to
see how dark your urine
is. You feel better, but
you're still incredibly
thirsty after taking a couple
of bananas and a little
bottle of coconut water. So
you go home and you start
drinking cold water and you
drink a lot of it over
the next two, three hours.
You know, it's around
two gallons and then you
start to urinate. And
the more you urinate, you
notice the lighter the
color. Each individual
urination is lighter than
the last one. And you
start wondering what
exactly is happening and
what are the processes
that have taken place to
create this big, you
know, range in the color.
So again, to put it simply,
in the schematic hot
yoga exercise, something,
something, it does
something to your urine.
You drink a lot of water,
it does something to your
urine. And we're going
to try to, you know,
elaborate on what happens in
these steps to give you
the differences in urine
So, again, big picture,
in a healthy individual in
steady state, water intake
has got to be the same
as water output, you know,
input output, you know,
must be equal. And
in this table over
here, we have basically
a rough breakdown
of the average
amounts that are lost.
These are some of the
obvious things that we know.
We get our water through
three major sources.
We drink water, we
ingested liquid water.
Our foods have
water in them. So it's
water contained in
food and then the water
that's produced by
aerobic metabolism. You
know, Krebs cycle breaks
down glucose to carbon
dioxide and water.
How we get rid of
the water? The major
way is through our
kidneys. Minor way,
you lose some
through the feces,
exhaled air, and sweat
production. But
sweat production
is geared and evolutionary
geared to help regulate
body core temperature
and not water balance.
And even though we can
have excessive amounts of
sweat during, you know,
either during exercise or
high temperature, it's
really not enough to cause
that much of a change in
the total amounts. And
you can see here, again,
the lion's share comes
from urine, and that's
where the most of the
regulation takes place. And
it's the only place where
it can compensate for
higher low water intake.
And we've talked about
our solute intake, and you
know that, you know,
kidneys can also regulate
variable amounts of
solutes, again, depending on
how much one can take.
It's interesting that, you
know, these are different
in all mammalian species,
depending on environment
and food availability,
one of the more fascinating
things I learned
are gorillas don't
drink a lot of water,
even though they are just so
much larger than humans are.
And gorillas,
80 to 90% of their water
intake is with food.
So, you know, they're
not, you know, especially
in nature. In zoos, they
drink a little bit more
water, but in nature,
almost all their water comes
from food sources, and
they're not big drinkers.
I'm always fascinated
by these variations.
So, let's use an
example. So in a
normal healthy diet,
we excrete around
600 milliosmoles
of solutes per day.
And that amount of
solute is dissolved in a
urine output of about
one and a half liters.
And that's average
amounts in healthy people.
But a couple of things
that kidney does is
regardless of the volume
of the excreted water,
our kidneys must excrete
the same amount of solutes
every day. And we can see
that a little bit in these
series of graphs on the
left-hand side. You can see
here the amount of solutes
in our plasma compared
to solutes and water in
our urine and urine versus
fluorate and urinary solute
secretion. You can see
that we get, we lose a
regular amount of solutes
regardless regardless of
how much fluid we ingest. In
this case, it's a one liter
addition of water. That's
around a quarter of a
gallon. You can see that
immediately uranosmolarity
will go down despite the fact
that plasma osmolarity is
only slightly decreased.
So, you know, uranosmolarity
goes down. that means
water concentration in the
urine is higher right the
concentration of solutes would
be lower which makes sense
if you drink a lot of water
you urinate more and you
can see that here as the
you know as urine flow rate
goes up uh osmolality is
down until you start self
-regulating um but the effects
on plasma osmolarity and
the amount of urinary
solute excretion is
tightly maintained.
Again, the water ends up
becoming much more of
an adjustable variable.
So, and that's basically
the kidney produces
urine having a wide
range of osmolarities.
And when the intake
of water is high,
the kidneys generate
urine with low osmolarity.
And the opposite, when you
want to conserve water,
kidneys generate urine with
extremely high osmolarity
and again that the amount
of urine coming out
can get adjusted to a
low of 0.5 but that's the
minimal amount anything
lower than that constitutes
indications of renal failure
and in fact renal failure
reduce both the concentrating
and diluting abilities
of the kidney so you end up
having massive amounts of
fluid and solute loss when
you have renal failure and
until you get nothing and
then you have toxic buildup.
So I have a very, you know,
interesting concept of
free water clearance when
it comes to the kidney.
You've talked about
clearance before and the
clearance of any compound,
so is the virtual volume
of plasma that would be
totally cleared of that
compound in a unit time.
And that's usually measured
in flow rates, mLs per
minute, liters per hour.
So if, for example,
the clearance of ion X
was 25 mLs a minute,
that would mean that
in one minute 25 mls
of your plasma would
have solute X completely
removed from it
now when we apply that
principle to water things become
a little bit strange
because how can you remove
water from water because that
doesn't really make sense
so there's some adjustments
in how one defines it.
So water loss is considered
two different ways,
sensible water loss and
insensible water loss.
And very simple, you can
just say by the names,
sensible, you're sensing
urination through sweat,
GI tract, and kidneys,
right? you if you have excess
water in feces you know
because then uh your
school your stool consistency
is different sweat
obviously if you you're
you're aware that it's
happening and these are
tightly regulated processes uh
obviously more so in the
kidney but up to a large
degree also in the gi
tract and and sweat glands
another you know so
sweat glands also
contribute to
insensible water loss.
When we have water loss
through exhalation and
through the skin. So, you
know, you can see that how
can it be both sensible
and insensible water loss?
Obviously, it's sensible
when you feel the sweat.
So hot, humid day, you
can feel the sensible
loss. But you still are
losing a little bit of
water during hot
environments, or if you have
a fever, and that
actually is not regulated.
On a hot, dry day,
you don't feel like
you're sweating. That's
one of the dangers of
being in hot, dry
environments is your ability
to judge your fluid intake
becomes a little bit
altered, because again,
you don't, you know, you're
not, you're not feeling this
loss. Anybody who's ever
gone hiking or driving
through the desert probably
can, can attest
to that. And this
kind of, this, this
graph shows it,
that those principles to us
in, you know, in, in, in
a very simple context.
Again, we want our total solute
excretion to be constant,
regardless of changes
in urine osmolarity and
urine flow rates. So if you
want to keep it constant
with high urine osmolarity,
then our urine flow
rates must be low. If we
want to have the same amount
excreted with high urine
osmolarity, then the urine
flow rates must be low,
right? High urine osmolarity,
a lot of solutes, less
water, so less flow. So
the total excretion, so the
urine flows would change
in order to make sure
that we keep our excretion
amounts the same.
So again, the clearance of
free water is calculation
of it. I'm not going
to ask you to calculate
even though you know i
have some equations here
i i promised you i'm going
to minimize the number
of equations and this is
probably the only times
you will see it it's
very simple stuff um so
this is flow rate urine
flow v and sometimes v
with this dot on top of
which I don't know how to,
you know, what that's called,
equals the clearance of
of whatever solute
we're looking for,
plus the clearance
of water. So if we
solve for the clearance
of water, you would have
urine rate minus the
clearance of water, right?
doesn't kind of make
sense, right? It's and then
if you solve for the
clearance of whatever x,
you would find that it
just the equation just
doesn't work. And the
clearance of water is not
the same as having urinary
water excretion over
the plasma concentration
of water. You know,
it's that this is
not the way it would
work out. So this is
the only way one can
look at the clearance of
water is by comparing it to
clearance of whatever solute
we want. But that's really
not, you know, I don't want
us to get too focused on
that. And this is one of
those times that it's just
very much simpler to understand
the connotations of it.
So again, we said clearance is,
if our clearance of
water is defined of the
clearance of water devoid
of all solutes. And that
doesn't, you know, what
does that mean? Well, all
it means is if we, if our
clearance is, you know,
positive,
the kidneys must
produce a urine
that's less concentrated
than plasma, right? So
what does that mean? That
means a dilute urine.
If this water is negative,
that means the urine is more
concentrated than plasma.
You know, that means that
you have to add water
in order to get the
certain ones. So, you know,
it's again, it's the
number itself is not as
important as whether it's
positive or negative.
And again, the ranges for
the values is related to the
osmolarity, and I have those
here. So isoosmotic urine,
if the osmolarity of urine
and plasma are the same,
if urinary osmolarity equals
plasma osmolarity, then
the clearance is zero, then
the clearance is whatever
urine flow rate we have.
We don't need to add
anything in order to remove,
in order to balance it out.
Dilute urine, if the urine
is more dilute than plasma,
right, if the
difference between urine
flow and the
clearance of the, you
know, the solute
clearance is positive,
right? So less concentrated,
more dilute urine,
and the exact opposite of
that concentrated urine.
If the urinary osmolarity is
higher than plasma osmolarity,
then it's negative, right?
You can't really, you're
not adding water in order
to balance that, the
urine osmolarity clearance.
You have to subtract it.
Kind of a weird, hard
thing to describe, but it's
just really all you have
to know is the implication
of positive free water
clearance versus negative
free water clearance, and
how that is related to
isoosmotic, hypoosmotic,
and hyperosmotic urine.
That's the kind of relationship
that you want to think of.
So how does that work in
the nephron? So let's go
over some basic principles
of water transport in
nephron segments. So remember
that water permeability
is different as we go
from the in the nephron
from Bowman's capsule
to the collecting ducts.
And in in order to generate
dilute urine, what we
want to do is get rid of
the solutes from the tubular
lumen, right, from the
ultrafiltrate from the urinary
component um in areas that
are impermeable to water
that's what we want to
do so then when that
happens the tubular fluid
is hypoosmotic compared
to to the blood uh
generation of a concentrated
urine is the exact
opposite we want to
drive water from the
tubular lumen into the
interstitial, right? So
we want to drive water
out in order to reabsorb
water and have more
concentrated urine
being created. So how do
we do that? Can we pump
water? No, we can't.
There's no such thing
as a water pump.
And the driving force that
one uses is osmosis, and
changes in permeability
to the specific tubular
contents. this creation of a
gradient in the interstitial
fluid is integral to the
creation of a concentrated
urine. And it's because
it's an osmotic gradient
in a confined area,
specifically the renal medulla.
And the final steps for making
concentrated hyperosmotic
urine is to regulate
water permeability and
to allow the content of
medullary collecting duct
water to equilibrate with the
hyperosmotic interstitium.
And if we can draw water
out of the lumen, then
we are reabsorbing water
and concentrating urine.
So that, so,
you know, we can go
over water transport in
all nephron segments,
but let's talk about,
yeah, and in both in
cases of diuresis and
anti-diuresis. So there's
a net absorption of
water across all along
the nephron, right?
but they all don't,
that change in
water reabsorption
doesn't affect the
osmolality of the
tubular fluid equally.
So we'll start off
with the proximal
tubule and here in
this section here.
And the y-axis gives us
the osmolarity of the
tubular fluid ratio to
osmolarity of plasma.
And you can see in
the proximal tubule,
regardless of the final
osmolality of the urine,
it always absorbs two
-thirds of the filtered load
iso-osmotically. So it
takes two-thirds of the
amount of solutes, take
two-thirds amount of water,
and that doesn't change
the concentration at
all, even though there
is a large bulk movement.
So the reabsorption
is the same in
the proximal tubule.
Water reabsorption
is the same as
solute reabsorption.
And you know all the
different solutes that are
changed accordingly.
And most of the water
absorption in this sequence
is done paracellularly,
but there's some
transcellular water movement
also through different
aquaporin isoforms.
So
distal convoluted tubule
and the loop of Henle
reabsorbs salt in excess of
water. And this is in this
section of this schematic,
and that's when we say
loop of Henle, I mean thin
descent thin ascending,
and thick ascending. So
three different segments.
The sum total of their
effects is more water
reabsorption than solute
reabsorption, even though the
contribution of the thick
ascending limb, I'm sorry,
the sum total of the
solute reabsorption is much
higher than water reabsorption,
even though the thin
ascending and thin
descending limbs have minimal
contribution to salviet
reabsorption. The activity of the
thick ascending limb and
the distal convoluted
tubule always makes sure that
we reabsorb salt in excess
of water. So when the
tubular fluid leaves the
distal convoluted tubule,
we've sucked out a lot of
the, removed a lot of the
solute, and the concentration
of the tubular fluid is
less than the concentration,
the osmolarity of, the
osmolarity of tubular fluid
is much lower than the
osmolarity of plasma, so
the tubular fluid is
hypoosmotic compared to plasma.
And when the final urine,
whether the final urine is
either dilute or concentrated,
really finally would
depend on the activity in
the last three segments here,
the collecting ducts and
the collecting tubules
and the collecting
ducts. And that's where
everything becomes
variable because it's under
the control of this
compound, which I have
mentioned before, but
we'll talk about it
in more detail in the
next couple of slides.
And that is
the water loss is controlled
by arginine vasopressin
antidiuretic hormone. Those
terminologies are used
interchangeably depending
on what you read. I use both
of them to kind of take
away the confusion. I call
it AVPADH, but they're the
same identical hormone.
And their function is to
regulate the fraction of
water reabsorption in these
three to four segments.
This should be three. I
don't know why it says four.
Sorry.
Right? In the classical,
yeah, that's three
segments, in the final
three segments of the year.
So in the next two slides,
we'll talk about how
this ratio changes when
we have water restriction,
hydropenia, or water excess.
Just we know that
this ratio will
change according to
these conditions.
So when we are restricted
with water, we must
concentrate urine and
excrete the minimal volume
of water that we have,
a state of antidiuresis.
How does that work? So
we can take another look.
Let's start off with
number one in the
proximal tubule. In
the proximal tubule,
there is no difference at
all in water excess or water
restriction.
The ratio is always one,
so we remove the same
amount of solutes and
the same amount of
water from the proximal
tubules. So there's really
no very little or no
change in osmolarity.
In the thin descending
limb of the loop of Henle,
the tubular fluid starts
becoming hypertonic.
right so how does
that work this area
is permeable and we
have it here in two
is permeable to water and
impermeable to electrolytes
so water is going to
leave the tubule go into
the interstitium and
leave salts behind so salt
concentrations salt good
concentrations will go up.
Once we get, and that
happens also to not as
high as a degree in the
thin ascending limb,
but you know, the
thick ascending limb
becomes the major
delineation point. So
what happens in the
thick ascending limb?
The thick ascending
limb, now the
tubular fluid
becomes hypotonic.
How does that happen?
Because A, we know
that the ascending limb
of the loop of Henle
is very important
in reabsorbing salt,
sodium chloride,
calcium, magnesium, and
it's very metabolically
active and it It
removes a large portion
of the solute concentration
in the tubular fluid
and reabsorbs it into
the interstitial. So
the tubular fluid becomes
less concentrated,
hypotonic.
And that's seen in the
downward slope that one
sees here, indicated
with the number three.
and then the urine, the tubular
fluid, it's not urine yet,
enters areas that are
sensitive to water, to AVP-ADH.
Now, the amount of solute
that's removed is so much
that actually, you know, the
concentration of the tubular
fluid is lower Osmolality
of tubular flow is lower
than the osmolality of plasma,
right? The urine is more
dilute once it leaves the
thick ascending limb. In the
distal and collecting tubules,
now we have sensitivity
to AVP-ADH. And in a context
of water restriction,
what we want to do is to
absorb as much water as we can,
right, because we want to
save our water. So the two
-pillar fluid becomes much
more hypertonic, you know,
compared to other areas.
That's because in water,
you know, in lack of
water, in hydropenia, when
you're thirsty, your AVPADH
levels are higher and causes
an increase in water
permeability. And remember,
this area is dilute, so
the water concentration
is high, so water is
driven out. And more driven
out, and then even more so
as you start getting into
the collecting duct. So
until you get to the final
stage, you will have a
tubular fluid that's much
more, you know, is that the
osmolarity is much higher
than plasma. It's, you
know, it's hyperosmotic.
So it ends up giving us
a more concentrated urine
because we want to
reabsorb the water and save
exact opposite
happens if we have
excess ingestion of
water now we want
to get rid of excess
water and you know
to you know and we
need the water to be
diluted so h it's
water diuresis and it's
For the first two stages,
well, first stage is identical.
The ability to
concentrate and dilute is
decreased in the loop
of Henle, as opposed to
conditions where we
have water restriction.
And in this context, because we
still have a more dilute area,
right, we still have the same,
you know, solutes are removed,
there's more water left,
but because we have no ADH,
because we have, you
know, AVP, ADH levels
are not elevated if
you have drank a lot of
water, right? if they're
actually depressed,
you will continue.
There's no water
reabsorption from these three
segments. And without water
reabsorption, the water
will stay in the tubular
lumen and come out as
urine, having, therefore,
we'll have a hypoosmotic,
relatively hypoosmotic
fluid remaining in
the lumen throughout
the remainder of
the nephron. So how
does ABP-ADH do this?
Well, it controls
plasma osmolality
and ABP-ADH is the
main way we do that.
And it regulates it by
sensing the ratio of sodium
chloride to water. Not
the only one. Glucose and
potassium also contribute, but
the sensor is osmoreceptors,
which are found in the
third and fourth ventricles
in the circumventricular
organs. This is one of
those areas that our capillary
architecture changes.
Circumventricular organs
have fenestrated capillaries,
so the availability
of water and sodium is
not restricted by any space.
Remember, the fenestrations
are big, large pores,
and they don't allow
any hindrance to the
back-and-forth motions of
electrolytes, and this
allows for rapid adjustments.
So ABPADH is a nonapeptide,
that's a small peptide,
nine amino acids, and
it's synthesized in the
paraventricular and superoptic
nuclei of the hypothalamus.
After it's produced, it's
packaged and transported
along the axons to the
posterior pituitary. So
it doesn't enter circulation
until it's stored in
the posterior pituitary.
And upon stimulus by the
osmoreceptors, it's
released and it goes through
the blood-brain barrier
into the system, systemic
circulation. I have a
schematic here on its effects.
ADH, AVP, and again,
this table here kind
of gives you similar
data and just a
different way to look
at the sensitivity of
segments of the
nephron to ADH and ADP,
and you can see that
it's the latter sections
of the nephron that
are sensitive to it.
Either way, ADH, ADP
has two receptors,
their own receptors,
the V1 and V2 receptors.
V1 receptors are found
on vascular smooth
muscle cells in our
resistant arterioles, and
they are very, very
potent basal constrictors.
Long sustained contractions
that are induced
by ADH-ADP when they
stimulate V1 receptors.
In the collecting duct,
it acts on V2 receptors,
the second member of
the family. There,
the sigla transduction
pathways are different.
In vascular smooth muscle cell,
like every other
vasoconstrictor that
you will see this
coming semester,
B1 will stimulate, it's a GPCR,
an increase in intracellular
calcium, and this
increase in intracellular
calcium leads to constriction
and increases in vascular
tone and eventual
increases in blood pressure.
In the collecting duct,
again, it's a
different receptor.
but the single transduction
system is different.
V2 receptors will activate
adenylate cyclase,
and that's indicated
here. They're both GPCRs,
by the way, and this
increase in cyclic AMP
will stimulate, one,
the insertion of
aquaporin-2 into
the basolateral, into the
luminal membrane, right?
Because that's where you want
the, you know, the regulation
to happen. And this increases
in aquaporin too will
lead to an increase in
water reabsorption. In this
context, water is going this
way. You have aquaporins on
the basolateral side,
but they are not the
same aquaporins that
are on the luminal side.
It's important because these
these aquaporins on the
basolateral sides are
not controlled by, are
not regulated by ADP. So
it increases water
permeability upon activation
of V2 receptors and
increase water reabsorption.
This increase in cyclic
AMP in general is
part and parcel of
the urgency to urinate
for coffee is because of
that, because caffeine,
among its many
pharmacological effects,
is a nice inhibitor of
phosphodiesterase, of
this guy over here.
So if you knock out
phosphodiesterase, you'll
have more cyclic AMP.
So it's partial, not
exactly all of it,
but that's part of
its pharmacology.
And that's really
basically the role of
AVP. So in anti-diuresis,
the levels go up.
In diuresis, the levels
go down. But that's not
the only way we can,
that the kidney regulates
urine osmolarity and urine
formation. And this is
actually the last part
of this, and I've left it
because it's probably
one of the more difficult
concepts in renal physiology,
and it's an area that
a lot of people always
have problems with. I've
tried to simplify it to
its basic core variables.
So what we want to do is
understand the mechanisms
involved in forming a hyper
- and hypoosmotic urine.
So we've already covered this.
We've covered the different
solute and water
permeabilities of each tubular
segments, the importance of
the osmotic gradient between
the tubular lumen and the
interstitium, or we'll talk
about that. We've talked
about the active transport
mechanisms that are involved
in this process with the
various parts of the nephron,
and then this exchange
mechanism that sustains
this hyperosmotic medullary
compartment. So a couple of
things, just basic principles.
Interstitial osmolarity
progressively rises
from the cortex to the
tip of the medulla.
And it goes anywhere
between, you know,
less than 100
millimolars or, you know,
milliosmoles, it
should be, you know,
a total millimolar of
our solutes, right?
As we go along, the
osmolarity, what,
will
increase because our
solute amounts are
increasing. And again,
we know why with sodium
chloride, because we've
talked about the different
pathways of sodium
chloride reabsorption.
We went over urea
a little bit, but
we'll go over it
a little bit more.
But the important thing is
the medulla is hyperosmotic
to blood plasma, regardless
of what state we are.
And the thick ascending
loop of Henle, it's water
impermeable, plays a key role in
the dilution and concentration
of urine by removal of
sodium chloride. And you
can see how that's important
later on. You'll understand
why this segment, when
it's the target of a drug
has such a profound effect
urea uh the role it plays uh
it's simple you know water
reabsorption in the thin
descending limb of henley
right we have always water
absorption um whatever urine
urea is in the lumen will go
up. As urea in the lumen
goes up, that increases the
gradient and actually will
stimulate urea reabsorption
to increase urea in the
interstitium. So urea goes up
in the lumen and then goes
up at the interstitium,
and that's why this area
becomes so profoundly, this
change in concentration is so
profoundly large is because
of the generation of this
trans-epithelial gradient.
So what are the
main components?
Well, the first one, again,
has to do with the
molecular biology of the
thick ascending limb of
the loop of Henry, tau.
We've talked about the
sodium NKCC, but the
other one is actually
the vascular architecture
and its relationship to
the tubular architecture.
And I have that here, And I
pointed arrows to show the
direction of the flows and
how they, you know, and
what they are. So this is our
afferent arterial here, you
know, goes into the glomerulus,
glomerulus comes out,
efferent arteriole, and
then you have the vasorecta.
And blood will go
down the vasorecta and
then come up through
and into the venules and
then go out into the
renal vein and leave.
So the direction that
it goes, it's the
opposite of the direction
that urine is going.
At one point are the
same right here in
the top parts, it's
in the same direction.
But once you go past it, go
into the medullary compartment,
you see that when we have
blood going one way, urine
is going the other way. And
that also reflects in the
descending parts of it. You
can see direction of urine
this way, and then direction
of blood the other way.
And that becomes very
important in what's called the
countercurrent multiplier
system. And I have that here.
But the important,
you know, again,
compartments, components are
the effectiveness of the
transporters and then
the medullary vasculature.
And this is very
interesting. Your medullary
vasculature is different
than cortical vasculature.
Everything is lower in
the medullary vasculature,
total blood flow permeability
volumes are lower.
So you get a lot of
accumulation of solutes.
You know, and that as
actually is interesting
because oxygen tension is
also lower in the medulla.
And I'll go, I'll go
into more detail of the
importance of that. I
think next semester when
when we talk about
regulation of erythropoietin.
So generally, the medulla is
anoxic compared to the cortex.
And remember that the kidneys
get 25% of our cardiac
output because they're
so metabolically active.
That's why if we have any
decrease in our cardiac
output, if there's any issue
with perfusion of the kidney,
the medulla is very,
very sensitive to these
changes. And what you end
up having is if you have a
decrease in any of the
oxygenation, nutritional
contributions of the blood.
The medulla is one of the
first places that feels the
pain first, and you start
getting death, cell death,
and tissue damage relatively
quickly once you have a
decrease in perfusion.
So what is the counter
current? Well, I just
said the current is the
counter. It's the opposite
of the flow of water
to compare to urine.
And what does it multiply?
And the multiplication
is it multiplies
interstitial osmolarity.
And by virtue of that
change in interstitial
osmolarity, by
increasing the gradient,
you affect osmolarity
in the urine.
And it's a system because
obviously it's not one. They
say one single pass would
only cause a 200 millim
osmolar gradient. That is,
you know, if we just did
everything once, that's the
only gradient you would get. But
that's not how the system
works. It's a recirculating
system with the solutes,
and that is the multiplier.
So the counter current
exchanger, by multiplying, by
via reabsorption and recycling
multiplies this delta
200 to much, much higher
levels. So we can get a
bigger range. And once we
get a bigger, bigger deltas,
we can create a more
hyperosmotic urine, and that's
important for mammals. In
fact, if you look at mammals
that are, have evolved,
survive in extremely dry
and arid environments, the
length of their nephrons
compared to the length
of same species,
for example, that has
evolved not to grow,
not to live in those
areas are much, much
different. They're much
longer and extensive.
So we went over urea,
but let's go over it
one more time and talk
about the recycling of
it. So it's complex,
like everything else,
you know, when is
everything simple for us?
So the kidney filters
of urea in the
glomerulus, and the
first thing it does is
give a hundred
percent filtered load.
Immediately proximal
tubule reabsorbed about
50% of it. And that's
I have indicated that
here by, it's indicated
here by box number one.
So as it goes through
the nephron and enters
the juxtamedullary regions,
you know, so the juxtamedullary
regions are portions of
the thin descending um
and then the actual loop and
then the thin um ascending
here
excuse me urea is
secreted into the
lumen so by a cycle
of reabsorption
and then secretion, we
go back to our filtered
load. But then urea
gets absorbed again
in the distal connecting
tubule and the
upper tau, and it gets
into the interstitium,
and what's remaining
is about 70%. It's
also the, you
know, the cortical
collecting duct also
contributes to that.
And then at the end,
in the more medullary
components of the
collecting duct,
you know, another 55
% or so is reabsorbed.
So what's left is
around 15%. And so we
get a large amount,
you know, like 85%
reabsorbed and stays
in the interstitium.
But that's not where it
stays because remember,
this isn't all this, you
know, our vasorecta is
superimposed on this
pathway. So urea will also
equilibrate into the vasorecta
and then get washed out.
So it keeps taking urea
out and recycles back
into the blood via the
ascending vasorecta for it
to go through it over
and over and over again.
So the net effect is
the kidney excretes
less urea into the
urine than it filters,
right? So the filtration
is much, much higher,
and what's remained
is much, much lower.
So during antidiuresis,
as tubular fluid
enters the tau, a
thick ascending limb,
luminal urea is several fold
higher than it
is in the plasma.
Because we have, you know,
because we have secretion, 100
% of everything is still there.
um the rest of the segments
have low permeabilities to
urea and but they have high
permeable permeabilities
to water so the urea
concentration will increase and
reaching concentrations are
eight to ten times higher
than you would find in plasma
so adh avp can increase
water and to a degree
urea permeability in the
intermedullary collecting
duct. And this will cause an
outward flux of urea from the
lumen into the interstitium.
So the result is urea
will accumulate in the
interstitium, and it's about
half the total osmolality in
the deepest part of the
inner medulla. I read this
somewhere, and I should have
kept it, and it's probably
somewhere in my office,
but this becoming a general
thought among renal
physiologists, this hasn't been
translated into textbook
yet, that this is very
important in species that require
a lot of water reabsorption,
don't drink a lot of
water, that it may not be
as important as a mechanism
to retain water in humans.
they believe that the AVP
-ADH system is much, much
more integral than the
creation of these, of this,
the osmolality gradients
for water reabsorption. But
that's, you know, that's
more of a philosophical
discussion, and I haven't
heard anything after that, but
it was an interesting topic
to have to have heard at
one point. And I would
have loved it because, you
know, this is a complicated
system. So in this last slide
here, the countercurrent
multiplier system is a
combination of tubular and
vascular exchange of solutes
and water. So we can,
they're breaking it down into
three key processes that
generate this medullary
osmotic gradient. One is the
active transport of sodium
from the loop of Henle to
the interstitium of the
outer medulla, and then you
have water diffusion from
descending to ascending
basa recta, and that's the
counter current, right? So
here, water is reabsorbed in
in, in, in these segments.
And water will then
go into the vasorecta as
the vasorecta goes down
and starts perfusing the
medulla. Now, when it goes
down and as you know
the the higher medullary
osmolales will uh
equilibrate in the vasorecta
and remember this is
changing all the time
because the blood is
continuously flowing
in and out so this keeps
removing washing everything
out and driving this this
pathway into this loop. And
then the last one is the
recycling of urea from the
inner medullary collecting
duct to the loop of Henle.
So these three main
processes are what create the
medullary osmotic gradient.
The descending basal
recta carries salt into
the inner medulla. They
raise the interstitial
osmolarity everywhere.
Interstitial salt
concentration rises,
so does the salt concentration
in the ascending basal
******. And then the steady
state is reached when
the salt added to the medulla
from the tubules is matched
by salt leaving the medulla
in the ascending basal
******, so taking the
blood away. So now the salt
content of the interstitium
is elevated and constant
because it's constantly being
fed by the reabsorptions
of sodium chloride
and urea, and then the
vasorecta keeps
revitalizing this system.
And that is the final section.
So you can see how
excess water can lead to
diuresis and cause a
decrease in urine color,
right? It's a good indication
of its concentration
and the exact opposite
happening during anti-diuresis.
And I'm sure that, you know,
there are questions, but please
don't hesitate to reach out
if there's any additional
things you want
to know. Well, thank
you very much, and
I will be speaking
to all of you later.